<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Untitled RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Coming soon!]]></description><link>https://PertuyF.github.io</link><image><url>images/favicon.ico</url><title>Untitled RSS Feed</title><link>https://PertuyF.github.io</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 20:02:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://PertuyF.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="quoteblock abstract">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First blog, first post</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Purpose</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I come from Biology and made my way toward imaging and image processing, entering the field of Bioinformatics a few years ago.
I started to use <strong>Python</strong> for this purpose and quickly grew fond of this wonderful language whose impact is hugely increasing in the scientific community.<br>
Being familiar with biostatistics and data analyses, I was curious of learning more general notions related to Data Sciences.
Doing so I discovered what brings me there, <strong>machine learning</strong>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Machine learning is not that common, at least not yet, in fundamental research for Biology.
I found that a number of tools I already used for image processing (the Numpy/Scipy ecosytem) where actually behind some of the main Python libraries for Data Sciences, like Pandas and Scikit-learn.<br>
Nevertheless it was an entirely new field to me, and even if I already knew some tools I needed theory.
I learned the basics of machine learning with MOOCs (especially the nice <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/intro-to-machine-learning--ud120">"intro to machine learning"</a> from Udacity), and experimenting using <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/">Kaggle</a> in the meanwhile.<br></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then I reached the part on <strong>Neural Networks</strong>&#8230;&#8203;<br>
I must say that I am fascinated by these things, they are getting all my focus right now and they definitely are what triggered that blog.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My purpose here is to share what I learn and experiment, step by step, starting with Neural Networks.<br></p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://PertuyF.github.io/2017/05/31/Hello-World.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://PertuyF.github.io/2017/05/31/Hello-World.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Introduction]]></category><category><![CDATA[Python]]></category><category><![CDATA[Machine_Learning]]></category><category><![CDATA[Deep_Learning]]></category><category><![CDATA[Data_Science]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Fabien Pertuy]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>